A shooter is taking aim at the president
of the United States.
For the Secret Service, it's their worst
case scenario, the nightmare they've
trained for for years. In the next few
seconds, each branch of the Secret
Service springs into action.
the protective detail, the counter
assault team, the airspace security
branch, the counter snipers, and the
emergency response team. What happens
next will decide the course of history.
If the Secret Service succeeds, today
will be forgotten soon enough. Keeping
the president alive is just business as
usual, the job the agency has
successfully done every day since the
death of JFK.
But if they fail, it will rock the
nation to its very core and threaten the
stability of America's democracy.
This is the moment that determines
everything. When instinct, training, and
sacrifice have to come together, or
else. Who are the people protecting the
president? How do they prepare for the
unthinkable? How does the Secret Service
actually work?
>> Confirm.
This video is largely based on the books
Zero Fail, The Rise and Fall of the
Secret Service by Carol Lenick and In
the President's Secret Service by Ronald
Kesler. Links in the description.
Fort Worth, Texas, 1963. The Secret
Service is exhausted. JFK is their
toughest assignment yet. He's constantly
traveling. Miami one day, DC the next.
His predecessors were older and spent
most of their days working inside the
White House where the president is
considered to be the safest. But JFK
loves to travel the world and attend to
his many adoring fans. Ishb.
>> And he has a taste for danger, sneaking
past his agents to swim in open water,
where he's swarmed by dozens of other
swimmers, throwing himself into crowds,
letting all kinds of unvetted guests
into his room night after night.
Keeping up with JFK is more than a
full-time job. It's a blur of double
shifts and all-nighters.
So tonight, a few agents are blowing off
some steam. They heard about a famously
shady nightclub called The Sellar, where
Texan beatnicks rub shoulders with
offduty cops, often resulting in brawls.
It's illegal to serve alcohol past
midnight. But The Seller is one place
you're sure to get a stiff drink at any
hour. And the agents stay way past
midnight, one as late as 5:00 a.m.
Four of them are assigned to protect
Kennedy the next morning, starting at
8:00 sharp.
Compared to today's Secret Service, the
agency protecting President Kennedy in
the 60s is bare bones, basically the
size of a municipal police force. There
are just 350 agents, most of them spread
throughout the US. Only 36 are assigned
to the White House with a rotating team
of six guarding the president. Keeping
the agency lean is partly due to an
American aversion to treating its
presidents like kings. Going back to the
founding fathers, people felt that the
Secret Service shouldn't be anything
like a royal guard until that cool
November morning in Dallas.
JFK likes to be seen. For this trip
through Dallas, he's insisted on riding
around in a convertible. And though the
Secret Service doesn't like it, he also
insists that his usual bodyguards ride
in separate cars. He wants to appear
accessible to the people.
>> Thousands are waiting to greet him in
downtown Dallas. At 1:25, the motorcade
moves into the downtown area. JFK and
Jackie smile and wave as their limousine
inches through Dallas at just 11 mph.
It's following a route that Dallas
newspapers published in advance. None of
the buildings on the route have been
inspected.
This is Clint Hill, the agent assigned
to protect Jackie Kennedy. Normally, he
stuck to her like a shadow, but today
he's following JFK's orders to give the
couple a little space.
Of the agents who went to the seller
last night, Hill was the first to leave
at 2:45 a.m. Today, he's also the first
agent on duty to recognize this sound
for what it is.
An attempt on the president's life. This
is Bill Greer, the agent driving
Kennedy's limo. He's not trained in
evasive driving. He slows down, waiting
for instructions on what to do next.
Another shot is fired. Clint rushes out
of the car. He runs to the limousine,
hoping to be at the president's side
before worse can happen. But he's too
late.
Clint throws himself on the trunk of the
car, only to find a gruesome aftermath.
Within 6 seconds of the first shot,
President Kennedy is dead.
>> If I had reacted just a little bit
quicker,
I could have, I guess.
Now live with that to my grave.
>> What happens next is history and it will
haunt the agency for years to come.
President Kennedy's death revealed that
something needed to change. But he
wasn't the first president to be killed
in office. 1865,
1881,
1901.
But now the United States is a global
superpower. The president is the most
powerful person on earth. The threats to
his life are multiplying and evolving.
And Kennedy's death traumatized the
nation profoundly. Nothing like this
should ever happen again. In the 60s and
70s, the Secret Service massively
expands its personnel and budget. No
longer will it be a small cadre of
glorified bodyguards. Gone are the days
when the service will hire any athletic
ex-Marine or patriotic beat cop.
Recruitment, training, and operational
protocols become way more rigorous. And
this is what six decades of evolution
looks like.
Protecting a president isn't just about
reflexes or muscle. It's about training
agents to think clearly under pressure,
spot patterns, and solve complex
problems fast. The good news is you
don't need to join the Secret Service to
sharpen those same skills. Brilliant is
built to turn the potential you already
have into real problem solving power.
You can build logic, math, coding, and
scientific thinking skills. It helps you
click with ideas that used to feel
abstract or intimidating. Their truth
and lies course is a perfect place to
start. You're given incomplete
information, build up clues, eliminate
what's impossible, and learn how to tell
real deductions from educated guesses,
figuring out exactly what's provable,
even when the situation is messy. With
Brilliant, you're not just watching
explanations. You're actively working
through step-by-step interactive lessons
until concepts truly make sense. It's
designed for ages 10 to 110. To start
learning free for a full 30 days, go to
brilliant.org/fern or scan the QR code.
You'll also get 20% off an annual
premium subscription and unlimited
access to everything Brilliant offers.
Protecting the president is a
roundthe-clock job. It's hours and hours
of mindn numbing boredom with occasional
moments of sheer terror. When these
moments come along, every split second
counts, and the agents response better
be automatic. There's no time to weigh
options. Their mission is zero fail.
The Secret Service calls any would-be
assassin a jackal. According to
journalist Ronald Kesler, jackals tend
to strike outside of the White House. A
president is most vulnerable when
arriving at or leaving an event. So, the
agents are currently on high alert. At
least 10 days before any external event,
agents head to the destination. Some
high-profile events, like the
president's inauguration, take up to a
year and a half. That's because the
Secret Service isn't just about making
sure a bullet doesn't hit the president.
It's about making sure it never enters
the event to begin with.
Agents are sent in advance to assess the
number of metal detectors needed,
scrutinize all access points, and
prepare explosive detection. Mainly,
they're thinking of the ways a jackal
could sabotage the event. Could he cut
the lights to create chaos? Could he
access the air conditioning units to
introduce poison gas? Could he sneak in
through a forgotten basement staircase?
The bulk of Secret Service work is
meticulous, detailoriented preparation,
making sure they're ready for days like
this. These special agents are the
protective detail, probably what you
think of first when you hear the name
Secret Service. They're the agents
expected to take a bullet for the person
they're protecting and then evacuate
them to safety. But they're just the tip
of the iceberg. There's the counter
assault team. They're the heavily armed
agents with the most dangerous role.
They're meant to charge at the source of
the attack and neutralize it before it
can reach the person they're protecting
with an automatic rifle or with a
flashbang grenade.
Then the protective detail can evacuate
the protectee to the presidential
limousine known as the beast.
The beast is a $ 1.5 million car
weighing about 20,000 lb. It takes the
president wherever he needs to go. It's
Americanmade, of course, and quite a bit
safer than Kennedy's convertible.
According to NBC News, it's bulletproof,
blast resistant, sealed off from
chemical attacks and stocked with a
supply of extra blood, exactly the
president's type. Not all of its defense
systems are known to the public, but
rumor has it it shoots tear gas.
Flanking the beast is the rest of the
presidential motorcade. Counter assault
agents trained in motorcade ambush
tactics travel in a car close to the
beast. Another Secret Service carries
intelligence agents who are tracking
people considered threats. If necessary,
they can jam these people's
communications.
After this, you should definitely check
out this fantastic episode by our friend
Neo for a full explanation.
In close communication with the counter
assault team is the eagle-eyed counter
sniper team, the best marksman in the
Secret Service. According to Ronald
Kesler, every month counter snipers have
to demonstrate they can still make shots
a thousand yards away. If they fail,
they're not supposed to work.
Here are plane closed agents who mingle
with crowds on high alert for threats
and vulnerabilities.
To blend in, they don't wear the
trademark earpiece. They're looking for
anyone suspicious, anyone sweaty, anyone
shifty, anyone who stands out in any
way. But it's a delicate operation, best
handled discreetly.
>> Look it. Look who it is.
>> Lots of people get starruck by a
president and they tend to act a little
weird. It's not unheard of for people to
weep, faint, or even throw their babies
in the air. And the Secret Service can't
go around tackling them all.
Agents in the crowd are also trained to
think like assassins in any given space.
How could they breach security if they
wanted to? If they detect any
vulnerability, they call the joint ops
center at secret service headquarters
who alert the protective detail by
earpiece. Some Secret Service
technicians are also photographing the
crowds to evaluate them later with
facial recognition technology. They're
looking out for whether particular
individuals keep showing up. Outside the
venue, we have the uniformed division's
emergency response team, the first line
of defense, often armed with P90
submachine guns and highly specialized
canines. Each dog sniffs up to a 100
cars a day for explosives and is trained
to attack any intruders. Later, they're
rewarded for their service with ball
play. The Secret Service is also
supported by local law enforcement and
emergency medical technicians. When
they're not actively protecting anyone,
Secret Service agents are constantly
training and reassessing past events.
Agents receive way more training than
they did in the 60s when they were just
handed a manual and expected to learn
the rest on the job. And a split second
from now, it'll be time to show their
stuff.
Just like in 1981,
back then, a mentally ill man named John
Hinckley Jr. became obsessed with and
stalked the actress Jodie Foster, who
starred in Taxi Driver. In the movie, an
aimless drifter plots to kill a
presidential candidate. Hinckley, an
aimless drifter himself, believed that
Foster would notice him if he did
something really great, like kill the
president. Just before his attack on
Reagan, he wrote to Foster, "You'll be
proud of me, Jodie. Millions of
Americans will love me. Us."
Foster didn't alert the FBI to
Hinckley's threats until after the fact.
>> The first time I knew that the FBI was
involved was when uh somebody called me
up and said, "Please come over and talk
to the FBI." But he was already on their
radar. About 6 months before he attacked
Reagan, Hinckley had been arrested for
attempting to board a plane with three
pistols. The plane was in the same city
where then President Jimmy Carter just
so happened to be.
Now Hinckley is outside a hotel in DC,
crouched in combat position. If indeed
he had wanted to kill Carter, he wasn't
able to get him. But Reagan will do.
Reagan is just six feet from his armored
car when Hinckley fires his rounds.
Agent Tim McCarthy doesn't even stop to
think. Instinct propels him to cover and
evacuate. He hurls himself in front of
the president. Two others nearby have
already been shot. Hinckley's third
bullet hits McCarthy squarely in the
torso. One bullet ricochets off the
bulletproof limousine and strikes Reagan
in the left armpit.
Unluckily for him, Hinckley has used
Devastator bullets designed to explode
on impact and cause maximum damage.
The president starts losing blood
quickly.
All this happens in 2 seconds, and the
seconds after that counted even more. If
Reagan had arrived at the hospital just
a few minutes later, he might not have
made it.
Meanwhile, the agents pounced on
Hinckley. They could have left that to
local police and traveled behind Reagan
to continue offering him protection.
Their thinking was that they didn't know
whether Hinckley was acting alone. But
after this event, according to Kesler, a
new policy was established. Secret
Service agents always stick to the
president. Every misstep becomes a
teachable moment that advances security
protocols for later. Hinckley's failed
assassination is considered one of the
Secret Services great successes, but it
was a close call. A man with a gun was
able to get just 4 and 1/2 m from the
president and very nearly kill him.
Clearly, security protocols needed to be
beefed up.
It's now standard procedure to have
magnetometers or metal detectors that
screen crowds at events. Beyond that,
the Secret Service found they needed way
better intelligence. 6 months before the
assassination attempt, Hinckley was
arrested trying to board a plane with
three handguns, information known to the
FBI. But under DOJ guidelines, the
arrest was deemed too minor and never
relayed to the Secret Service. In
hindsight, that omission deprived
presidential protectors of a major red
flag, a prior weapons arrest timed to
coincide with a presidential visit. The
Secret Service now works more closely
with the FBI. They've also developed an
elaborate system for classifying just
how threatening an agrieved person is.
Say you make the mistake of drunkenly
boasting to a crowded bar that you're
going to kill the president. If the
Secret Service catches wind of it,
according to Kesler, you might be
considered a class one threat and an
agent could show up at your house for a
serious chat. But unless you have prior
military training, a documented history
of mental illness, or a concrete reason
for the service to believe you might try
to carry out your plans, you won't be
bumped up to class 2 or three. Class 3
threats are considered the most
dangerous, those with a serious intent
to kill and the ability to do so.
They're monitored very closely. The
Secret Service receives an average of 10
threats per day. Most are against the
president. Not all can be taken
seriously. Many threats are mailed
directly to the White House. Would be
assassins seem to think that the
president will read their letter
personally, and they want to be heard. A
letter can give the Secret Services
forensic division a lot to work with.
DNA, fingerprints, and ink samples they
can compare with the ones in their
international ink library.
Since the early 80s, profilers have
interviewed and studied assassins like
Hinckley and Sirhan Sirhan, who killed
Robert Kennedy. This helps the Secret
Service understand the motivations of
these individuals who are often paranoid
loners seeking attention and notoriety.
Often, but not always.
The first bullet narrowly misses the
president. A counter sniper tries to
take the assassin out, but he's already
vanished into the chaos. The protective
detail pounces on the president, forming
a human wall. Another shot is fired,
this time from the crowd. Is that gun
made of white plastic? A bullet grazes
the shoulder of an agent in the detail.
The counter assault team heads straight
for the line of fire. Meanwhile, the
remaining detail escorts the president
off the podium, hoping they reach the
beast in time and that the real threat
isn't overhead. the threat that the
service has braced itself for since the
morning of September 11, 2001.
>> President George W. Bush is in Florida
for the morning. He's joined a second
grade class for their reading lesson.
He'll be back in the White House by
lunchtime. The event has been publicized
for a week. It's a feel-good photo op to
celebrate Bush's commitment to
education. The Secret Service is well
aware that the world can see exactly
where the president is. When the first
plane hits the World Trade Center, an
agent in Bush's security detail receives
intelligence. He asks if the attack is
isolated to New York and if the
president's security is compromised.
No answer. Nobody knows. Minutes pass.
The Secret Service grows more agitated.
>> Both Twin Towers now are on fire. The
second plane hits and Bush is informed
that America is under attack.
>> On page 153,
>> the age-old tension between the White
House and the Secret Service has reached
a fever pitch. One team's job is to
project a competent image of the
president, which requires the president
to engage with citizens.
The other team's job is to keep the
president safe. The less he's seen in
public, the easier that is to do. Nobody
knows what to do. The Secret Service
wants Bush out now, but the White House
press secretary doesn't want to scare
the children or the public watching.
>> So Bush stays put for seven excruciating
minutes.
>> Good job. Go on.
>> E,
>> go on.
>> The chaotic aftermath of that morning
revealed more holes in the Secret
Service coverage. For one thing, not all
important agents were briefed on how to
adequately protect their assignments in
case of a national emergency. There
wasn't a system for getting them to
military controlled shelters, nor were
the agents granted the power to do so.
Instead, they were treated like mere
bodyguards, elite ones. But still, they
had to obey other staffers with no
expertise in security, like the White
House press secretary.
The Secret Service had become really
good at preventing attacks from crazed
lone gunmen. But in the face of a
sophisticated terrorist attack aimed at
the president, they needed a whole new
playbook and more authority. After 9/11,
the Secret Service rewrote its emergency
action plans. It was made sure that no
political staffer could overrule a
Secret Service agent attempting to
evacuate a president to safety. and the
government decided that maybe, just
maybe, the president's bodyguards should
work closely with the people tracking
terrorists. A year and a half after
9/11, the Secret Service was drafted
into the new Department of Homeland
Security. The Protection Mission was now
understood as a form of
counterterrorism.
Shortly after the attack, the Secret
Service established a new unit, the
Airspace Security Branch, responsible
for monitoring and controlling the
airspace of the president's current
location.
Will today be the day they have to down
a rogue drone?
But the sky remains calm. The president
makes it into the beast,
and that's when he starts exhibiting
strange symptoms. tiny pupils, profuse
sweating, wheezing, and convulsions.
The nerve agent Navach is a swift and
brutal killer. It can take a victim down
in less than 2 minutes. To kill or
incapacitate a victim, a nerve agent
needs to penetrate the skin or be
ingested or inhaled, meaning that only
someone in very close contact with the
president could have administered it. Is
there a third assassin? among them. The
Secret Service will deal with the holes
in their security later. Now, the focus
is on saving the president. That's where
the hazardous agent mitigation and
medical emergency response team comes
into play. Also known as Hammer.
Today, Hammer agents will save the
president's life.
The first wouldbe assassin was sniffed
out and tackled by the K-9 protective
unit as he attempted to escape the
venue. He's now in jail awaiting trial.
The second assassin with the 3D printed
gun, was shot by the counter assault
team. He died on the spot. And the
third, the guy in the Secret Service
itself, a career agent who rose through
the ranks to the president's personal
security detail, turns out he's a
sleeper agent sent by a foreign nation.
It isn't yet clear which and they don't
know how he infiltrated the service.
Recently, the agency has been strained,
struggling to fill key positions. Could
there have been a lapse in their vetting
process? They'll be sure to interrogate
him intensively to find out.
Our story may be an unlikely scenario,
but it's just one of many possibilities
that the Secret Service prepares for
every day. Threats to the president have
only expanded in recent years. So the
service is now trained to deal with
previously unheard of attacks.
The war on terror gave the Secret
Service more power than ever. More
budget, more reach, more respect, but
also more responsibilities that
stretched them beyond their capacities.
Internally, the machinery started to
rust.
The Bush and Obama years saw waves of
scandals that undermined the AY's
reputation and their motto worthy of
trust and confidence. In one case, a
senior agent reportedly took a female
informant up to his hotel room. She died
that night from a drug overdose. He was
later promoted. Other agents were caught
stealing federal funds, having sex with
minors, drunk driving on White House
grounds, becoming embroiled in
prostitution scandals, engaging in
racist hazing of black agents, brawling
in bars. Plus, there were several near
misses during Barack Obama's presidency.
>> A bomb sniffing dog to the bag.
>> Obama received four times as many
threats as previous presidents, largely
motivated by racism. Some commentators
have said it's a miracle he's still
alive.
In the service, morale is often low and
turnover is usually high. It's not easy
to find qualified replacement agents.
Not just anyone is willing to take a
bullet for 48k a year. Plus, the job
requires agents to travel constantly,
move frequently, and work huge amounts
of unpaid overtime. It's common for
agents to quit and find better pay and
job conditions at other federal agencies
or start their own security firms.
Still, since JFK, the Secret Service has
done its job. No dead presidents since
1963.
But there was one particularly close
call.
>> Want to really see something that said,
"Take a look at what happened." In
Butler, Pennsylvania in 2024, Donald
Trump was nearly assassinated as he was
campaigning for his second presidency.
Check out our video that breaks down
that event. People still wonder, how
could an assassin get to an unguarded
roof with a clear line of sight to
Trump? It's widely considered a major
failure of the Secret Service.
>> Sir, this could have been our Texas
schoolbook depository. I have lost sleep
over that for the last 17 days. just
like somebody to hold.
>> Six agents were suspended and the
director stepped down.
>> Just 2 months later, another attempted
assassination of Trump rattled the
service. And it's possible there have
been many more incidents of nearly
successful assassinations throughout US
history. We just didn't hear about them.
Maybe that's the real secret of the
service. all the times history almost
changed then didn't.
Hey, we hope you enjoyed the video.
Videos like this take a lot of work by a
whole team of creators and it's our
sponsors that make it all possible. If
you have a sec, check out Brilliant so
we can keep the videos coming.